Stuart William David Grieve

Postdoctoral Research Associate

University of Edinburgh School of GeoSciences Drummond Street Edinburgh, EH8 9XP United Kingdom **८** +44 (0)7812 729 542 **S.grieve@ed.ac.uk**

O sgrieve

Blog: sgrieve.github.io/

Google Scholar: Stuart W D Grieve

Appointments

2016- **Postdoctoral Research Associate**, University of Edinburgh

Topographic analysis and landslide modelling software.

Research Assistant, Cardiff University

Education

2016

2013–2016 **Ph.D. in Global Change** University of Edinburgh

*Uncovering signatures of geomorphic process through high resolution topography.*Supervisors: Dr Simon M Mudd and Dr Tristram C Hales (Cardiff University)

2011–2012 M.Sc. in Geographical Information Science (Distinction) University of Edinburgh

Thesis Title: An automated analysis of the southern San Andreas Fault to explore topography's relationship with tectonics.

Supervisor: Dr Simon M Mudd

2007-2011 **B.Sc. (Hons.) in Geology and Physical Geography** (2:1) University of Edinburgh

Thesis Title: The Influence of Climate Change on Landslide Sediment Yields in the Northern

Lake District.

Research Statement

A primary component of my research is the development of open source tools which facilitate reproducible topographic analysis, with a particular focus on the processing of high resolution topographic data. Such software allows repeatable experiments to be performed on both terrestrial and Martian landscapes, at a range of scales spanning individual hillslopes to continental scale features. I am also interested in the application of cutting edge GIS and computer science techniques to enhance surface process research, through the analysis of complex spatial information combined with novel data collection approaches.

I employ such software and techniques to develop an understanding of how sediment transport processes are reflected in landscape morphology, particularly how sediment is transported from hillslopes into channels. The mechanisms of this transport range from the motion of individual particles through to large scale slope failures and debris flows. I work to link forest growth models to shallow landslide hazard, to better understand slope stability in locations where forests are rapidly changing, in many cases due to human impacts. The variability of steady state landscapes is poorly understood and with high resolution topographic analysis I aim to bridge the gap between models and reality and identify topographic signatures of local scale processes, which converge to shape landforms at scales beyond their initial region of influence.

Teaching Statement

My teaching, as with my research, focuses on the implementation and application of quantitative and computational methods, as a framework to understand Earth surface processes. I am passionate about engaging students to interpret landscapes and the processes which act upon them both in a classroom and field setting. I have experience of teaching theoretical and applied GIS, either within the context of physical geography or a number of other disciplines (transport planning, infrastructure, crime research, archaeology) at both an undergraduate and postgraduate level. Aside from teaching physical geography and GIS, I also enjoy teaching scientific programming to students, giving them a grounding in data analysis and visualisation which can be employed throughout their time in education and beyond. Such skills are vital for students and I believe I am well placed to teach these skills within a physical science context.

Technical Skills

Accomplished programmer comfortable with object orientated concepts and a range of languages (C++, Python, Java, Visual Basic, Perl) and the use of version control (git, subversion) to manage large projects. Extensive experience in desktop (ArcGIS, FME, Whitebox, QGIS) and web based (MapBox, Mapguide) GIS to solve complex spatial problems. Managing large spatial and non-spatial datasets using SQL databases (Oracle, PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite). Processing raw LiDAR point clouds to produce bare earth DEMs.

Employment

2015–2016 2012–2013 **GIS Consultant and Field Course Leader**, GeoBus, University of St Andrews **GIS Trainee** Forth Crossing Bridge Constructors

Publications

- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., *How long is a hillslope?* Earth Surf. Process. Landforms. doi:10.1002/esp.3884
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., Milodowski, D.T., *A nondimensional framework for exploring the relief structure of landscapes*. Earth Surf. Dynam., doi:10.5194/esurf-4-309-2016
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Milodowski, D.T., Clubb, F.J., Furbish, D.J., *How does grid-resolution modulate the topographic expression of geomorphic processes?* Earth Surf. Dynam. Discuss. doi:10.5194/esurf-2016-28
- Mudd, S. M., Harel, M.-A., Hurst, M. D., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, and Marrero, S. M., *The CAIRN method: Automated, reproducible calculation of catchment-averaged denudation rates from cosmogenic radionuclide concentrations*, Earth Surf. Dynam. Discuss., doi:10.5194/esurf-2016-18
- Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Valters, D.A., *A statistical framework to quantify spatial variation in channel gradients using the integral method of channel profile analysis*. J. Geophys. Res. Earth Surf., doi:10.1002/2013JF002981

Conference Presentations

INVITED TALK

Grieve, S.W.D., Reproducible geographic analysis: Insights from geomorphology. Presented at GIS Update, Edinburgh.

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., *Constraining hillslope sediment flux using high resolution topographic data*. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *The Relationship between Drainage Density, Erosion Rate, and Hilltop Curvature: Implications for Sediment Transport Processes*. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

- Mudd, S.M., Hurst, M.D., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Milodowski, D.T., Clubb, F.J., Attal, M. *Detecting geomorphic processes and change with high resolution topographic data.* Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna.
- Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Milodowski, D.T., Hurst, M.D., Clubb, F.J., Valters, D.A., *LSD-TopoToolBox: Open source geomorphology.* Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *The Relationship between Drainage Density, Erosion Rate, and Hilltop Curvature: Implications for Sediment Transport Processes*. Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Parker, R.N., Hales, T.C., Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *Precipitation and soil accumulation history modifies future landslide hazard*. Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Parker, R.N., Hales, T.C., Mudd, S.M., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, *Climate change has limited impact on soil-mantled landsliding*. Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna.
- Grieve, S.W.D., Mudd, S.M., Hales, T.C., *How long is a hillslope?* Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco.
- Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., **Grieve, S.W.D.**, Valters, D.A., *A statistical technique* for identifying channels of different steepness in transient landscapes. Presented at the EGU General Assembly, Vienna.

Classroom Teaching Experience (Course Level)

- Quantitative Methods in Earth Sciences, Laboratory Demonstrator (3rd year)

 Geomorphology, Laboratory Demonstrator and Tutor (2nd year)

 Object Oriented Software Engineering Principles Laboratory Demonstrator (1)
- 2014–2015 Object Oriented Software Engineering Principles, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- 2014–2015 Object Orientated Software Engineering: Spatial Algorithms, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- 2014–2015 Principles of Geographical Information Science, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- 2014–2015 Introduction To Spatial Analysis, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- 2014–2015 Distributed GIS, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- 2014–2015 Spatial Modelling, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
- Earth Surface Systems Course Assistant (1st year)

	Fundamental Methods in Geography, Laboratory and Field Demonstrator (2nd year)
	Geo-Visualisation, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
	Advanced Spatial Database Methods, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.) Further Spatial Analysis, Laboratory Demonstrator (M.Sc.)
	Earth Surface Systems, Laboratory Demonstrator and Tutor (1st year)
	Field Teaching Experience (Course Level)
	Cyprus field course (4th year honours)
	Fundamental Field Methods in Geography (2nd year)
	Service
	Reviewer: Earth Surface Processes and Landforms.
	Currency Reviewer : Reference Module in Earth Systems and Environmental Sciences, Elsevier.
	Session Chair M.Sc. GIS postgraduate conference, University of Edinburgh.
	Funding Received
	British Society for Geomorphology Student Travel Grant Award: £750
	NERC Cosmogenic Isotope Analysis Facility: <i>Hillslope-channel coupling in a steady-state land scape</i> .
	P.I.: Tristam Hales (Cardiff University) Co. I. Simon M. Mudd, Robert Parker (Cardiff University) and Stuart W. D. Grieve. Award: £19,320
	Safe Software Grant Program Award: Software licence for FME Desktop Edition
	SAAS Postgraduate Students' Allowances Scheme Award: £3400
	University of Edinburgh Postgraduate Bursary Award: £1300
	Professional Memberships
	Professional Memberships American Geophysical Union